<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2464 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2464.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4861 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4861.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC8174 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC8200 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8200.xml">
]>

<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc strict="yes"
      toc="yes"
      tocdepth="4"
      symrefs="yes"
      sortrefs="yes"
      compact="yes"
      subcompact="no" ?>


<rfc category="std"
     docName="draft-kline-6man-pmo-00">
    <front>
        <title abbrev="IPv6 PathMTU Option">IPv6 PathMTU Option</title>

        <author fullname="Erik Kline" initials="E." surname="Kline">
            <organization>Loon LLC</organization>
            <address>
                <postal>
                    <street>1600 Amphitheatre Parkway</street>
                    <city>Mountain View</city>
                    <region>California</region>
                    <code>94043</code>
                    <country>US</country>
                </postal>
                <email>ek@loon.com</email>
            </address>
        </author>

        <date/>

        <area>General</area>
        <workgroup>Internet Engineering Task Force</workgroup>

        <keyword>IPv6</keyword>
        <keyword>RA</keyword>
        <keyword>Router</keyword>
        <keyword>Advertisement</keyword>
        <keyword>PathMTU</keyword>
        <keyword>MTU</keyword>
        <keyword>Option</keyword>

        <abstract>
            <t>
This document describes an IPv6 Neighbor Discovery (ND) PathMTU Option (PMO)
for inclusion in Router Advertisements (RAs). This allows some environments
greater flexibility to support, for example, a higher MTU for on-link or
intra-administrative-domain communications than for broader Internet
communications.
            </t>
        </abstract>
    </front>

    <middle>
        <section title="Introduction">
            <t>
This document describes an IPv6 Neighbor Discovery (ND) PathMTU Option (PMO)
for inclusion in Router Advertisements (RAs). This allows some environments
greater flexibility to support, for example, a higher MTU for on-link or
intra-administrative-domain communications than for broader Internet
communications.
            </t>
        </section>
        <section title="Requirements Language">
            <t>
The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED",
"MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
described in BCP 14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/>
when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.
            </t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="format" title="Option Format">
            <t>
Any IPv6 link-local prefixes listed within a PathMTU Option MUST be ignored
and SHOULD be logged for review by an administrator.
            </t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="processing" title="Receiver Processing Rules">
            <t>
Nodes compliant with this specification do not change their processing of
RAs that contain no PathMTU Options. Whether the RA contains an MTU
Option or not, the processing is unaltered by this document.
            </t>
            <t>
Any MTU value lower than the IPv6 minimum MTU (i.e. 1280,
<xref target="RFC8200"/>
<eref target="https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc8200#section-5">section 5</eref>),
SHOULD be logged for an administrator as a configuration error and MUST be
treated as though the IPv6 minimum MTU had been the encoded value.
            </t>
            <t>
Let the "Link MTU" be the MTU as it would be determined were no PathMTU Option
present. This may be: the value specified in an MTU Option, a value specified
in a separate document that covers operating IP over a particular link type
(e.g., <xref target="RFC2464"/>), or derived by other means (e.g.
administrative or a hint from a sub-IP layer mechanism). The Link MTU MUST be
used for all link-local destinations.
            </t>
        </section>
        <section title="notes">
<t>
IPv6 Router Advertisement Path MTU Option

TLV
Type = TBD
Length = units of 8 octets, including TL bytes, with zero padding
         at the end as required
 { 4 byte MTU,
   1 byte # of prefixes,
   [ { 1 byte of prefixlen,
       0-16 bytes of prefix address, trailing zeros dropped },
     ...
   ]
 }
 { 4 byte MTU,
   1 byte # of prefixes,
   [ { 1 byte of prefixlen,
       0-16 bytes of prefix address, trailing zeros dropped },
     ...
   ]
 }

MTUs less than IPv6 min MTU must be ignored and treated as 1280.

Regular MTU option applies to on-link destinations.

In environments where on-link nodes do not communicate with one another,
either by policy or by practice, setting the MTU option value to the path MTU
value for all destinations through the advertising router is a practical
measure. In other words, since there is no on-link communication of note,
supporting higher MTUs for on-link destinations is of no operational value,
especially when not doing so can burden hosts with endless PathMTU discovery.

However, even in these environments there may be changes in Path MTU (e.g.
a change in upstream provider to one with a lower MTU). It can still be
operationally useful to separate the Path MTU from the on-link MTU.


Examples:

[1] RA MTU 1500
    RA PathMTU
      - 1422, 1, 0

1500 on-link (fe80::/10, ff02::/16, and 2001:db8::/64),
and 1422 for all other destinations.

[2] RA MTU 9000
    PIO 2001:db8:1:2::/64
    RA PathMTU
      - 1500, 1, 0,
      - 9000, 1, 48, 2001:db8:1:::

[3] RA MTU 1422
    PIO 2001:db8:1:2::/64
    RA PathMTU
      - 9000, 2, 64, fe80::,
                 64, 2001:db8:1:2::

9k to 2001:db8:1::/48, fe80::/10, and ff02::/16
1500 to ::/0

Implementations compliant with this document interpret the PathMTU option
in the following way:

[2] The original MTU option (if present), or the hardware-defined MTU if not,
SHALL be interpreted as the MTU for on-link destinations. If the RA has a
non-zero default router lifetime (i.e. it advertises itself as a default
router) and there is no zero CIDR length route in the PathMTU option (or the
PathMTU option is absent) this MTU SHALL also be used for all

[2] If a PathMTU value is found for a given destination according to the
lookup and parse rules of section (ref), this PathMTU option MUST be honored
when using the advertising router as the next hop (subject to other device-
or interface-specific constraints).

[3] A
<xref target="RFC4861"/>
</t>
        </section>
    </middle>

    <back>
        <references title="Normative References">
            &RFC2119;
            &RFC4861;
            &RFC8174;
            &RFC8200;
        </references>
        <references title="Informative References">
            &RFC2464;
        </references>
    </back>
</rfc>
